Hi, welcome to this week's videos! This week we are
स्वागत है इस हफ्ते के वीडियो में |इस हफ्ते हम
only going to talk about Pivot Tables and I'm going to guess that this is a little
बात करने वाले हैं सिर्फ़ Pivot tables के बारे में और मैं अनुमान करती हूँ की यह थोड़ा
bit of a relief to you,
आपको राहत देगा
because if you did last week's exercise, this is probably
क्यूंकी अगर आपने पिछले हफ्ते का एक्सर्साइज़ किया होगा तो
more or less what you ended up with. So, I am going to assume that you have seen
आप लग भाग यहा पे होंगे | तो मैं यह मानूँगी की आपने
enough new formulas for a week.
काफ़ी फ़ॉर्मूला देखा है इस हफ्ते के लिए |
So, this week no new formulas, we are only going to talk about how to analyse
तो इस हफ्ते कोई नया फ़ॉर्मूला नही होगा, हम बस बात करने वाले है कैसे
your data using pivot tables.
डेटा को आनलाइज़ कर सकते हैं Pivot table को इस्तेमाल करके हुए |
Also, we are not doing the hardware store anymore.
और इस हफ्ते हम कोई हार्डवेर दुकान भी नही खोलने वाले हैं |
I think we've seen enough of the hardware store for a little bit,
मेरे हिसाब से हमने अभी तक काफ़ी सारे हार्डवेर दुकान देख लिया है
so this week
तो इस हफ्ते हम
we are going to be running a bar. The spreadsheet for the bar is a little bit
एक मधुशाला चलाने वाले हैं | मधुशाला का स्प्रेडशीट थोड़ा बहुत
similar to the hardware case because we again have
मिलता जुलता होगा हमारे हार्डवेर दुकान से क्यूंकी हमारे पास फिर से
an export from a register system, where we keep track of everything that we sell in the bar.
एक एक्सपोर्ट है रिजिस्टर सिस्टम से जहा पे हम हिसाब रखते है मधुशाला के बिक्री का |
But we have some more information in this case, because in addition to the date,
पर हमारे पास और थोड़े ज़्यादा सूचना है अभी, क्यूंकी दिनाक के अलावा,
the time, the type of beer that we're selling, and the quantity,
समय है, किस तरह का बीयर हम बेचने वाले हैं, कितना बेचने वाले हैं
we are also keeping track of who buys the beers.
और हम हिसाब रखने वाले हैं कौन हमारा बीयर खरीद रहा है |
So, let's assume all our customers have some sort of loyalty card,
तो हम अनुमान करते हैं की हमारे सारे ग्राहको के पास एक तरीके का लायल्टी कार्ड है
so we know exactly who buys what at which time
तो हमे पता है सही से की कौन क्या खरीदता है और किस समय पे
and that of course allows us to do a lot of nice analysis.
और यह खबर हमे मौका देता है बहुत सारा अनॅलिसिस करने |
So with this data,
तो इस डेटा से
we also have a list of all the beers that we are selling in another worksheet,
हमारे पास एक सूची है, सारे बीयर के जो हम बेच रहे हैं एक और वर्कशीट में
all the beers that are there and let's assume we just Googled
सारे बियर है जो मिलते हैं और सोचते है की हमने गूगल किया
for all the beers and we found a nice list of all beers.
इन सारे बियर के लिए और हमे एक अछा सा सूची मिला सारे बियर का |
So, of course, a question that we could ask ourselves is:
तो अभी एक सवाल हम अपने आप से पूछ सकते हैं  :
how many of each of the beer types have we been selling?
हर एक तरह के बियर का कितना हम बेच रहे हैं ?
So we can use a COUNTIF function for that, I am sure this is a pretty
तो हम COUNTIF  का इस्तेमाल करते हैं उसके लिए
familiar function by now.
जिस से आप परिचित है |
We look in the register log how many times have we
हम अपने रिजिस्टर लोग में देखते हैं कितने बार हमने
sold this specific beer.
एक तरीके का बियर बेचा है |
Simple, right? You already know that. So question: is this formula
आसान, है ना? आपको पहले से पता है | तो सवाल है :
actually correct? Can you spot anything that might be wrong with this formula?
क्या यह कार्य असलियत में सही है? क्या आप बता सकते हैं क्या ग़लत हो सकता है इस फ़ॉर्मूला में?
I'll give you one second to think about it.
मैं आपको एक सेकेंड देती हों सोचने के लिए |
So I hope you were yelling at your computer screen while I was pausing,
आशा है आप अपने कंप्यूटर पे चिल्ला रहे होंगे जब में तोड़ा विश्राम ले रही थी ,
because obviously there are few things
क्यूंकी असलियत में थोड़ी चीज़ें हैं
that are wrong with this formula. The first thing is that beers prefix,
जो ग़लत है इस फ़ॉर्मूला में | पहला है की बियर का प्रीफिक्स
we don't need it. Excel adds it always
वो हमे नही चाहिए | जो एक्सेल जोड़ देता है हरदम
if you switch worksheets, but it's actually better to remove it.
अगर आप अपना वर्कशीट बदलते हैं , पर यह बेहतर होगा अगर आप इसे निकाल दे तो |
But something else is wrong with this function, I don't think COUNTIF is the
पर और भी कुछ ग़लत है इस कार्य में, मुझे नही लगता COUNTIF सही
right thing to use, because we have a quantity there.
कार्य है , क्यूंकी हमारे पास इधर मात्रा है |
So, what we do with a COUNTIF is just count
तो जो हम करते हैं COUNTIF के साथ, वो है हम सिर्फ़ गिनते हैं
all the rows that are there, but that's not what we want.
सारे रो जो हैं लेकिन यह वो नही है जो हम चाहते है |
We want to use the SUMIF function, because we want to have the sum
हम SUMIF कार्य इस्तेमाल करना चाहते हैं , क्यूंकी हम राशि
of all those quantities we are selling. So we have to change our function
चाहते हैं सारे मात्रा का जो हम बेच रहे हैं | तो हम अपना कार्य बदलने वाले हैं
a little bit,
थोड़ा सा
because now we also need to tell Excel what the column is
क्यूंकी अभी हमे एक्सेल को यह भी बताना होगा कौनसा कॉलम है
that we are summing, and if we add that function, then
जो हम सम करने वाले हैं, और अगर हम इस कार्य को जोड़ते हैं तो
the formula is correct.
यह फ़ॉर्मूला ठीक हो जाता है |
However, this formula is correct, but something
हालांकि यह फ़ॉर्मूला ठीक है , कुछ है
is a little bit inconvenient here, because you see here in this
जो थोड़ा असुविधाजनक है इधर, क्यूंकी आप देख सकते हैं
'Times sold' column
'Times sold' कॉलम में
we only have zeros at this point. Because the list
हमारे पास सिर शून्य है अभी | क्यूंकी जो सूची
of all the possible beers that we can sell is so long
है सारे बियर की जो हम बेच सकते हैं बहुत लंबा है
that the first ones just are not occurring.
जिस के वजह से पहला वाला आ ही नही रहा है |
So I have to click Sort, I have to go
तो मैं अभी sort क्लिक करती हूँ . मुझे
to the ribbon, click sort, say I want to have
पहले रिब्न को जाना होगा और sort क्लिक करना होगा, और मुझे सबसे
only the largest numbers on top. And then, as you can see,
बड़ा संख्या उपर चाहिए | और फिर जैसे आप देख सकते हैं
we can see what beers we have exactly been selling. So it's quite a hassle to
कौनसा बियर हम बेच रहे हैं | यह
get everything done.
करने में थोड़ा परेशानी होती है |
And in addition to that, we could ask
और इसके अलावा हम और भी
more difficult question. Suppose our boss comes in and even though we changed our
कठिन सवाल पूछ सकते हैं | सोचिय हमारे बोस आते हैं और भले है हमने हमारा
business from a hardware store to a beer shop we still have the same boss.
कारोबार बदल दिया है हार्डवेर से मधुशाला, हमरे बोस वही है |
Isn't that interesting?
है ना दिलचस्प?
And she asks very interesting questions like: what beers
और वो हमसे एक दिलचस्प सवाल पूछती है जैसे : कौनसा बियर
have been most sold after 11 p.m.?
हमने सबसे ज़्यादा बेचा है 11 बजे के बाद?
Those are probably interesting to know because you want to know what beers are
यह बहुत दिलचस्प होगा जानने क्यूंकी आप जानना चाहते हैं कौनसा बियर
popular early
पसंदीदा है
in the evening and what beers are more popular late at night.
शाम को औंर कौनसा बियर पसंदीदा है रात को  |
So suppose we have to add an analysis like that,
तो सोचिए हमे एक अनॅलिसिस जोड़ना होगा इस तरह
it's going to be a little bit cumbersome. Because, first of all, we have to
यह तोड़ा बोझिला होगा | क्यूंकी सबसे पहले हमे
add another column
और एक कॉलम जोड़ना होगा
saying what times are after 11.
जो बताता है कौँसे समय है 11 के बाद |
And your first intuition might be to use
और आपका सबसे पहला अंतर्ज्ञान होगा
an IF function there, but it's actually not needed. You can just use
IF कार्य को इस्तेमाल करने, पर इसकी ज़रूरत नही है | आप आप उपयोग कर सकते हैं बस एक
a comparison function
तुलना कार्य का
as a proper formula in Excel. So, here we try
जो एक फ़ॉर्मूला है एक्सेल में | तो इधर हम
a first attempt, we say if the time is bigger than 23.
पहला प्रयास करते हैं , हम कहते हैं अगर समय 23 से बड़ा है |
However, that's not really working, because you see here in this case, we
हालांकि यह काम नही करेगा क्यूंकी आप देख सकते हैं हमारे पास
have 11 p.m.
11 p.m. है |
However, we still get FALSE. And the reason for that is the way that Excel works with
वैसे भी हमे FALSE  मिलता है | और इसका कारण है एक्सेल जिस तरह से काम करता है
times, is that it saves the time
समय के साथ वो है
as the fraction of the day. So 5 p.m. is more or less like 0.7 here.
दिन के अंश के रूप में समय को रखता है | तो 5 p.m  0.7 के आस पास है इधर |
You can see that if you change the time into a number.
आप देख सकते है अगर आप समय बदल देते हैं संख्या को
So, for proper comparison with times we have to compare with a time.
तो सही तुलना के लिए समय के साथ तुलना एक समय के साथ करना चाहिए |
So we have the time, 23 hours, 0 minutes and 0 seconds,
तो हमारे पास समय 23 घंटे , 0 मिनिट और 0 सेकेंड है
and if we use that as a comparison then we actually get TRUE here
और अगर हम इसे इस्तेमाल करेगें तुलना के लिए तब हमे असलियत में TRUE मिलता है
in the case where the time is above 11. So I was cheating a little bit. I told
इस हाल में जब समय 11 से उपर है | तो हमने इधर थोड़ा छल किया है | मैने
you in the beginning of the video that I wouldn't show you any new formulas.
वीडियो के शुरुआत में कहा था मैं आपको आज कोई फ़ॉर्मूला नही दिखाने वाली हूँ |
This is a new formula, but I hope you're going to let this one go, because
यह एक नया फ़ॉर्मूला है पर आशा है आप इसे माफ़ कर देंगे क्यूंकी
it's very simple and it's
यह बहुत आसान है और यह बस
only for time comparison.
समय के तुलना के लिए है |
So, with this function we can now add our analysis,
तो इस कार्य से हम एक और अनॅलिसिस जोड़ सकते है
because we can
क्यूंकी हम
change our 'Times sold' from a SUMIF
बदल सकते है हमारे 'Times sold ' को SUMIF
into a SUMIFS, where we use multiple conditions to sum on.
से 'SUMIFS'में जहा पे हम बहुत सारे कंडीशन्स इस्तेमाल करते हैं हिसाब करने के लिए|
We have to change our formula a little bit, because how the SUMIFS works
हॅमे हमारा फॉर्मुला थोडा बदलना होगा क्युंकी  SUMIF  जीस तॅरह से काम करता है
is, we get first the column that we are summing,
है , पहले हम वो कॉलम लेते है जिसपे हम जोड़ करने वाले है
and then a list of conditions. So we picked the quantity column first,
और उसके बाद कंडीशन्स के सूची जोड़ने वाले है | तो पहले हम मात्रा वाली कॉलम को लेते है
and then we say we want to have the name of the beer,
और फिर हम कहते हैं हमे उस बियर का नाम चाहिए
as the first condition. It has to be equal to the first column of
पहले कंडीशन के हिसाब से | यह समान होना चाहिए
the beers worksheet,
हमारे बियर वर्कशीट के पहले वाले कॉलम के साथ ,
and then the second condition is our time,
और फिर दूसरा कंडीशन होगा समय
'After 11 p.m.' has to be TRUE.
'11 p. m  के बाद', TRUE होना चाहिए |
So it's quite a long formula, but it gets the job done. However, as you can see here,
यह एक बहुत लंबा फ़ॉर्मूला है , पर यह हमारा काम ख़तम करता है | हालाकी, जैसे आप इधर देख सकते है
the column is now not sorted yet, because it is still sorted
कॉलम अभी तक सॉर्ट नही हुआ है , क्यूंकी यह अभी भी पुराने
in the original order. So if you want to sort it,
तरीके से सॉर्ट हुआ है | तो अगर आप सॉर्ट करते है
again, we have to click sort. Here you can see
फिर से , हम sort  को क्लिक करते हैं | आप इधर देख सकते हैं
those values are not properly sorted yet. So if we click sort now,
यह मूल्य सही से सॉर्ट नही हुआ है | तो अगर हम sort क्लिक करते है तो
something strange happens. Here you see:
कुछ अजीब होता है | आप देख सकते है :
Hey, that is not the correct value! The links
यह सही मूल्य नही है | यह कड़ी
again, have been updated and that's because we forgot this time,
फिर से अपडेट हुआ है और यह है क्यूंकी हम भूल गये समय
I hope you were screaming again at the computer screen. We forgot to remove that beers
आशा है आप फिर से अपने कंप्यूटर पे चिल्ला रहे होंगे | हम बियर का
prefix. So if you remove that,
प्रीफिक्स निकालना भूल गये | तो अगर आप इसे निकालते है तो
then we get the correct result. But that was a lot of work, right?
हमे सही उत्तर मिलता है | पर यह बहुत काम था ना?
A simple query: what beer is best sold after 11 p.m.?
एक छोटा सा सवाल : कौनसा बियर सबसे अछा है बेचने के लिए 11 p.m.के बाद?
We have to add another column, change our formula
हमे और एक कॉलम जोड़ना होगा, फ़ॉर्मूला बदलना होगा
and make sure that we don't forget to remove the prefixes
और भूलीएगा नही प्रीफिक्स को निकालने के लिए
and that we don't forget to sort. So what I hope that you take away from these videos,
और सॉर्ट करना भी | तो आशा है आप इस वीडियो से
is: formulas are meant for calculations. If you are calculating
जो सीखते है वो है : फॉर्मुलास हिसाब करने के लिए बना है | अगर आप कुछ हिसाब कर रहे हैं
a sum or an average, a formula is fine.
एक सम या एक आवरेज का तो फ़ॉर्मूला इस्तेमाल करना चाहिए |
But as soon as you start to do really analysis, you are
पर जैसे ही आप हिसाब करना शुरू करते हैं अनॅलिसिस करने,
diving into your data, you're asking yourself questions like:
आप डेटा में डूब जाते है और अपने आप से सवाल करते है :
what's the most popular beer on a Saturday
कौनसा बियर शनिवार को सबसे ज़्यादा पसंदीदा है
if the temperature is below zero degrees? Something like that.
अगर तापमान शून्य से कम है ?
If you're analyzing your data formulas quickly go out of hand. And I think you
अगर आप अपने डेटा फॉर्मुलास को आनलाइज़ करते है तो यह तुरंत हाथ से निकल जाता है | और सोचती हूँ
saw in this example that
आपने इस उधारण में देखा होगा
that just happens very quickly. So remember: formulas are not for analysis
की यह कितने जल्दी होता है | तो याद रखिए : फॉर्मुलास अनॅलिसिस के लिए नही है
and of course then, what is for analysis?
तो क्या है अनॅलिसिस के लिए?
Pivot tables! More about pivot tables in the next few videos.
Pivot tables,  हम और बात करेंगे pivot tables  के बारे में अगले कुछ वीडियो में |